<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ in the clouds, or Gods comming to iudgement A short treatise, very necessary in these euill and dangerous times, for all those which desire that the day of the Lord, may be their day of ioy.</title>
            <title>Christ in the clouds.</title>
            <author>Warner, John, fl. 1635.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14778</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25078</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106604</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842317</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842317</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6962</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14778)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6962)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 583:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ in the clouds, or Gods comming to iudgement A short treatise, very necessary in these euill and dangerous times, for all those which desire that the day of the Lord, may be their day of ioy.</title>
                  <title>Christ in the clouds.</title>
                  <author>Warner, John, fl. 1635.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for F. Coles, at the vpper end of the Old-Baily, neere Newgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Warner.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judgement Day --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6962:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6962:1"/>
            <p>CHRIST In the Clouds, <hi>OR</hi> GODS comming to <hi>Iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſhort Treatiſe, very neceſſary in theſe euill and dangerous times, for all thoſe which deſire that the day of the Lord, may be their day of ioy.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MAR. 13. Verſes 35.36.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Watch, for yee know not when the Maſter of the houſe will come: whether at Euening, or at mid-night, or at the Cock-crowing, or at the dawning: leſt he come ſuddenly, and finde you ſleeping.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>F. Coles,</hi> at the vpper end of the Old-Baily, neere New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, 1635.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:6962:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6962:2"/>
            <head>Chriſt in the Clouds: or Gods comming to Iudgement.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Picuriſme</hi> and <hi>Atheiſme</hi> are two ſins moſt hainous and deadly: the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> beléeues there is no God: him <hi>Dauid</hi> confutes, <hi>Doubtles there is a God which iudgeth the earth.</hi> The <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure</hi> beléeues there is no Iudgement after Death: him <hi>Salomon</hi> doth ſéeme to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, <hi>Remember that for all theſe things thou muſt come to Iudgment.</hi> There is no Chriſtian, I think,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.3</note> but beléeues that there ſhall be a day of Iudgment: <hi>But when this day ſhal come, none knows, for of that day and houre, no man knoweth, neither the Angels of heauen, but my father only.</hi> But although no mans reach is able to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine when that day and houre ſhall be yet it may plainly be demonſtrated and ſhown both from the Prophets and Apoſtles, that this iudgement day is néere at hand, &amp; will moſt ſuddenly come vpon vs. It is the mercy of the holy Ghoſt to man, in holy Writ to inſert theſe caueats, and to put man in mind of the Iudgement day, and
<pb facs="tcp:6962:3"/> thrée ſpeciall cauſes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 That we may be terrified from ſin.</item>
               <item>2 That we might be admoniſhed to the true and ſincere worſhip of God.</item>
               <item>3 That wee might be ſtrengthened in our faith, leſt that great and terrible Day ſhould come vpon vs vnawares, and ſo find vs vnprouided.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Since the foundation of the world, wée know the time; when the diſſolution of the world ſhal be, we are altogether ignorant: yet we may iuſtly Propheſie and preſage thus much, ſince ſinne and impiety is now come to that height, that it can by no ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding ages be aggrauated, &amp; that vertue and godlineſſe are ſo deſpiſed and vilified among impious men, that they can neuer hereafter be leſſe eſtéemed: Who cannot then perceiue, or is ſo dull ſighted, that is not able to apprehend and fore-ſée the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to bée at hand? Now is that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of <hi>Hoſea</hi> verified; <hi>There is no truth, nor mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea 4.</note> 
               <hi>nor knowledge of God in the Land, which appeareth by the curſing, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, murthers, thefts, and adulteries which now aboundeth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 7.</note> So that now, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Micah</hi> hath it: <hi>The godly man is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht from the earth, &amp; there is no iuſt man among the ſons of men.</hi> Thus <hi>Hoſea, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah,</hi> nay, all the Prophets do agrée in one,
<pb facs="tcp:6962:3"/> whereupon ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe: When righteous men periſh from off the face of the earth, the earth muſt needs periſh alſo, becauſe the godly are the pith &amp; marrow of earth.</hi> For as a trée without pith &amp; moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture ſoone drieth vp, ſo the preſent world muſt néeds decay, when the righteous that ſhould vphold it, are not to be found in it: for this cauſe, as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> hath it: <hi>In the City is left deſolation, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is in the gates thereof, becauſe of their manifold iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe ſaid, As in the <hi>dayes before the Flood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> 
               <hi>they were eating and drinking, marrying, and giuing in marriage, vntill the day of the flood came and tooke them away: So alſo ſhall the comming of the Sonne of man be,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of prophaneſſe and too much ſecurity. Suppoſe that this Prophecy ſhall be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled vpon our preſent times, and that God will ſay to vs, as he did to <hi>Noah, I will deſtroy you with the world.</hi> O vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy and miſerable ſhall that man bee then, that hath not God for his guide. But to the end wee may the better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, that we are they, vpon whom the ends of the world muſt come, there is no better a ſigne among thoſe which Chriſt himſelfe gaue before, than this:
<pb facs="tcp:6962:4"/> Namely, <hi>That the Goſpell of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall be preached in all the World, for a witneſſe to all nations, and then ſhall the end come.</hi> Which is as much as to ſay according to S. <hi>Chryſoſtome: To accuſe and reproue thoſe that would not beleeue the Goſpell.</hi> The ſame it is of <hi>Hillarie: The Apoſtles being diſperſed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the world, and the Goſpell preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then ſhall the fall of Ieruſalem, and the end be.</hi> Neuertheleſſe, there are both lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; vnlearned of this opinion, that ſince the world, ſo long after theſe propheſies, hath continued as before, that the end is not néere, and that the world ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſtill immutable; but let them perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in their opinions. For ſince S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Cyprian, Chryſoſtome,</hi> and Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> were of opinion, that ſince the Goſpell, in their time was preached to all Nations, long after their time the world could not endure; ſurely then it is moſt probable, that this is the age in which the end muſt come. Now that we may haue ſome proofe that the world cannot endure long, becauſe the Goſpell is ſaid to bée preached to all Nations; heare Saint <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> who was of opinion that there was in his time, no Nation that was ignorant of the Goſpell of Chriſt: for he ſaith; <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:6962:4"/> they haue no Preacher, yet they cannot but heare the opinion of the Faith of their neighbour Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Proſper</hi> confirmes: No part of the world is without the Goſpel of Chriſt, ſome of all ſorts, and of all Nations haue knowledge of Chriſt: I could induce a Cloud of opinions: but let <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſerue for them all: <hi>The Goſpell is preached, that the world may be deſtroied.</hi> To conclude this point, ſince probably by this great motiue we are induced to beléeue that the end is at hand, and that the day and houre thereof is vncertaine, it ſhould ſtirre vs vp to a more holy courſe of life, leſt that our deſolation and confuſion ouertake vs vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares.</p>
            <p>But to the end that wée may the better vnderſtand and beléeue, what hath béene before ſhewed, the word of God is a moſt firme argument to informe vs of the truth of Chriſts ſudden comming, and that this preſent Age, is the laſt Age of the world; for the Spirit expreſly ſaith: 1 <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth</hi> 4. <hi>That in the latter end ſome ſhall depart from the Faith, giuing heed to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing ſpirits, and Doctrines of Deuills, ſpeaking lyes in Hypocriſie, and hauing their conſciencce feared with an hot iron, &amp;c.</hi> And againe, know this alſo, <hi>That in
<pb facs="tcp:6962:5"/> the laſt dayes perillous times ſhall come; for men will bee louers of their owne ſelues, couetous, boaſters, proud, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, diſobedient to Parents, vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, vnholy, without naturall affection, truce-breakers, falſe accuſers, incontinent, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, louers of pleaſure more than of God, hauing the forme of godlineſſe, but denying the power thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre the Apoſtle, which words S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> handling, ſaith, All things that were foretold, are fulfilled, and the end of the world drawing neere: The Propheſies are come to paſſe, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the men, and the mindes; for now (if euer) is the perfection, or rather im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of all the ſinnes, the Apoſtle names to bée the fore runners of the end. Why doubt wée then, that the end is not at hand, or why feare we not rather, that a ſudden end will preuent our procaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Repentance? As bodies are ſicke before death, and as infirmity and ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe are the true fore-runners of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration betwéene the Body and the Soule: Euen ſo fareth it with the world, it now langniſheth, and is corrupt, it now lies ſicke, and therefore it muſt needes come to confuſion, and to an end. For
<pb facs="tcp:6962:5"/> deadly ſickneſſe is a fore-runner of death; all things now ſuffer their defect, and let no man wonder at it, for man now is borne in ſuch defect, in reſpect of the birth of man in former times: but what is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the preſent condition of mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, is ſupplied in the faculties of his minde, and what is defectiue in the ſtrength of his members, is compleat in the ripeneſſe of his vnderſtanding, which is for the moſt part implyed not in liberall, but in diuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh arts; not in the ſtudy of learning, but of pleaſure. Onely wit and maturity is reſident in man, the onely <hi>Idea</hi> and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment of the Image of God in man. What can we otherwiſe but thinke, that the time is at hand, wherein mortality ſhall put on immortality; wherin the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of the fleſh being laid aſide, the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous body of the Church ſhall bée coupled to her glorious head, the communication of Saints ſhal be conſummate, and Chriſt ſhall inioy his Spouſe in continuall loue and vnion? In the meane time with <hi>Paul, Vnhappy men that we are,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from this body of death, that wee may paſſe ſecure to the body of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then let euery good Chriſtian in theſe wicked times wherein deſtruction hangs ouer our heads, with good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> pray,
<pb facs="tcp:6962:6"/> 
               <hi>Lord I am oppreſſed, doe thou vndertake for me;</hi> and ſince the day of deſtruction is ſo néere vs, wee intreat thée ſince it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for vs, that thou wouldeſt teach vs ſo <hi>to number our dayes that we may apply our hearts to wiſedome:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 39.</note> And ſince thou haſt pronounced that ſeruant happy, <hi>who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Maſter when the came, found vigilant and watchfull:</hi> Grant, Lord, we beſeech thée,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.37</note> that ſince it is manifeſt, that long it cannot bée before thou come, that wée may bée fitted and prepared for thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and bée found with oyle in our Lampes, and ſo in happineſſe enter thy Bride-chamber with ioy: and let vs, good Lord, thinke the Day moſt neere, leſt while the day of death or iudgement bée thought to be farre off, it preuent the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouident, and while long life is expected, it quickly forſake the wicked and guilty perſons. Our mindes are very deſirous, if we could, to know the day of death, and diſſolution. But if wee could attaine to the knowledge thereof, what would it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit vs, ſuppoſe the conſummation of this world to be after ten, twenty, or forty, or a hundred yeeres, what is this materiall? is not the terme of life the conſummation of each man? Why then are thou ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about the laſt day of iudgement, ſince
<pb facs="tcp:6962:6"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s thy end leaues thée, Iudgement ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind thée, and how ſuddenly death ſhal find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee, thou art altogether ignorant: For as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n other things not regarding things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aining to our ſoules, wee altogether are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſied in things common, ſaying: This man is an Adulterer, this man a Theefe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his man a falſe-hearted fellow, that man proud, but no man hath a care or feeling of his owne ſins far worſe.</p>
            <p>So doth euery man neglecting his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd; he would faine learne when the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall day of diſſolution ſhall be, which Day whether it be néere or farre off, it doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing concerne vs, ſo each man regard his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euerall end. For ſince thou art borne, 'tis moſt certaine thou muſt dye, and it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain after death commeth, that Iudgment may be far off, yet thy laſt day is at hand. Therefore prepare thee for this day: for if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his day find thée vnprouided, the day of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udgment ſhall find thée ſo likewiſe, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hou ſhalt rue for it:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 50.</note> Conſider this all yee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat forget God, leſt he teare you in pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, and there bee none to helpe: For our God ſhall goe, and ſhal not kéepe ſilence. A fire ſhall come before him, and it ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery tempeſtuous round about him, for God himſelfe is Iudge. And the Day of Iudgement will quickly be at hand, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent
<pb facs="tcp:6962:7"/> the ſpeede thereof: It will ſpéedil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> come, preuent it I ſay, bée thou ſpéedil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conuerted. And as the Prophet <hi>Daui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> aduiſeth vs, let vs runne before the fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Iudge, with confeſſion of our fault<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and true contrition for the ſame. And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reaſon why thou knoweſt not his com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming is, that thou mayeſt alwayes be pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared for it: for it is in thine owne powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how thou mayeſt expect his comming, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> therefore defers his comming, that whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he comes he may not daunt thee. Behold, hée is not yet come, he is in Heauen, thou art on earth; he deferres his comming, do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not thou deferre this time of repentance leſt it for euer, though too late, repent th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his comming: For in that day, it wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be too late to repent; therefore pray no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that his Kingdome come, which thou fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſt comming, but rather correct thy ſelfe that thou pray not againſt thy ſelfe: To<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>day hee cals vpon thee, that hée may not in that day condemne thee. He that ſhall then be thy Iudge, is now thine aduocate and hée now cals vpon thee, that tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wouldeſt leade a godly life Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſet the day of Iudgement before ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eyes, which way ſoeuer wée goe, let v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> carry the memory of it with vs, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will bring this profit with it, that we ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:6962:7"/> not onely meditate on the horrour and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>truction of that day, but alſo wiſh for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccompliſhing of the ſame, which makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he wicked to tremble when they heare it approacheth.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith: <hi>Let vs from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mong our ſelues repeat theſe things, and with others, there ſhall be a reſurrection, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> day of Iudgement, and a time of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for all our workes, whether good or bad:</hi> and this will cauſe that the minds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth of good and bad, be not conuerſant in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he vanities and pleaſures of this world, and bee not tempted to any wickedneſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut rather to vndergoe any thing to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vpon them here, than to incurre the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore-ſéene puniſhment of euerlaſting fire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ereafter.</p>
            <p>This made <hi>Dauid</hi> cry out: <hi>Eſtabliſh my fleſh in thy feare, for I haue been afraid to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare thy iudgements.</hi> To conclude this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oint ſince wée all muſt appeare before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Iudgement-ſeat of Chriſt, that euery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne may receiue the thing done in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy according to that he hath done, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be good or bad, and knowing the terror and Iuſtice of the Iudge of al men, that ſhall iudge the World in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and conſidering the puniſhment that then ſhall be impoſed on the wicked:
<pb facs="tcp:6962:8"/> 
               <hi>That ſhall be turned into Hell with the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that forget God.</hi> Let vs heare and follow <hi>S. Hillaries</hi> aduiſe, In all the courſe of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> liues, the memory of the laſt and grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Iudgement is to be planted and grafted i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our hearts, for happy is that man that dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what he muſt doe in remembrance of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laſt day and why?<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.36.</note> heare the words of <hi>Ieſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the ſonne of <hi>Sirach; Whatſoeuer thou ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt in hand, remember thy end, and thou ſhalt neuer doe amiſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much ſhall ſuffice, there ſhall bée a day of Iudgement, and that that Day i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> néere: Now ſomewhat remaineth to bé<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpoken of the manner of this Day, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> terrour thereof, that the wicked being touched with the vnderſtanding of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame, might be driuen nearer to God: <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that day</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) euery mans work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be made manifeſt, for the day ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> declare it, becauſe it ſhall be reuealed by the fire, and the fire ſhall try euery mans worke of what ſort it is.</hi> The time is now come when Iudgement muſt begin at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> houſe of God, and if it firſt beginnes with vs, what ſhall the end be of them that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey not the Goſpell of God? and if the righteous ſcarcely be ſaued, where ſhall the vngodly and ſinner appeare? where will they hide themſelues in that terrible
<pb facs="tcp:6962:8"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, wherein there ſhall be nothing, but weeping and gnaſhing of téeth, howling, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amentation, and repentance too too late? when the foundations of the mountaines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall bée mooued, and the land ſhall bée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urnt with fire; when as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Heauens ſhal paſſe away with a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyſe, and the firmament ſhall melt with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eruent hear, the earth alſo and the works <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat are therein ſhall be burnt vp:</hi> when, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s God himſelfe ſaid in the Goſpell:<note place="margin">Mat. 24.29</note> 
               <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unne ſhall be darkened, the Moone ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot giue her light, the Stars ſhall fall from Heauen, and the powers thereof ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>haked:</hi> Where will the wicked then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old themſelues, where will Adulterers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>runkards, where will curſers and ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers appeare? where will the luxurious, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceiuers, proud, vncleane and filthy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſons be found? what, vnhappy as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, can they then plead for themſelues, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppeaſe the anger of the iuſt Iudge of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en and earth? ſurely nothing. Howle ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore, O ye wicked that forget God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the day of the Lord is at hand, and it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall come as a deſtruction from the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; for the Lord ſhall lay the Land <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſolate, and ſhall deſtroy the ſinners <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hereof out of it, he will puniſh the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or their euill, and the wicked for their
<pb facs="tcp:6962:9"/> iniquity, hee will cauſe the arrogancie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the proud to ceaſe, and will lay low the hautineſſe of the ambitious worldling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what feare, and what horror, what terror and amazement ſhall there ſeize vpon, and poſſeſſe thoſe that are marked out for eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall deſtruction? In the Name of God le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs therfore while we haue time, rouze ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelues vp; whiles there is time, let vs cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rect and amend our ſelues that wée neue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be brought to theſe Tortures of body an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoule. Let vs rather preferring the ſimp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>city of the Doue, and the chaſtity of the Turtle, with the ſpirituall feathers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> graces, lift our ſoules vp into heauen b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our prayers, that ſo wée may be alwaye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ready to reſigne our ſoules and bodies int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the hands of our Redeemer, with ioy an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alacrity of ſpirit.</p>
            <p>But that we may the better heare and vnderſtand the terror of that day, to auoid the ſame, wee will heare the Prophets what they fore-tell. <hi>Gird your ſelues and lament you prieſts, how leye miniſters o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Altar, lie all night in ſackcloath ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Miniſters of my God: For the meate of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fering, and the drinke-offering, is with holden from the houſe of God.</hi> Alaſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for the day of the Lord is at hand, and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the Almighty ſhal it come
<pb facs="tcp:6962:9"/> 
               <hi>Blow a trumpet in Zion, and ſound an ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in thy holy mountaine, let al the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the land tremble: For the day of the Lord commeth, for it is nigh at hand; a day o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> darknes and of gloomings, a day of clouds, and thicke darkneſſe; for great is the day of the Lord, and very terrible, ſure tis a great day wherein ſo great a God greatly to be praiſed, and to be feared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all gods, ſhal come to iudgement, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o reward all men for their doings.</hi> Tis a great day, after which there ſhall bee us change of time, no courſe of dayes ſhal fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow; which day in it ſelfe ſhal containe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euerlaſting condemnation, or ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without end.</p>
            <p>It is a very terrible day, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Malachy,</hi> ſéemes to giue the reaſon of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. <hi>For behold, the day commeth, that ſhall burne as an Oven, and all the proud, and al that doe wickedly, ſhall be as ſtubble, and that day that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſhall burne them vp, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith the Lord of hoſts;</hi> leauing them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther root nor branch: And as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> hath it. <hi>Our God ſhall come, and ſhall not keepe ſilence, a fire ſhall deuoure before him, and it ſhall be very tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous round about him, he ſhall call to the heauen from aboue, and to the earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that he may iudge his people.</hi> For
<pb facs="tcp:6962:10"/> God is Iudge himſelfe; who, therefore wil endure the fury of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> day, where the ſtrong ſhall be thus weakned &amp; oppreſſed, and where ſhe proud, and all that doe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly, ſhal be burnt vp as ſtubble? who wil not ſtand aſtoniſh'd, where the root with the branch ſhall be plucked vp and conſumed? what wicked man, what ſinner then dareth <hi>to appeare where the iuſt ſhal ſcarſe be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Per.</hi> 4.</note> But many men, partly out of dull ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity, and partly being oppreſſed with croſſes and vexations of this life, do little eſtéeme of the terror of this laſt day, and do ſéeme as being prepared for this day, very earneſtly to wiſh and deſire the ſame: But the Propht <hi>Amos</hi> 5.18. doth threaten theſe men, ſaying, <hi>Wo vnto you that deſire the day of the Lord, to what end is it for you?</hi> The day of the Lord is darknes, and not light, as if a man did fly from a Lyon, and a Beare met him; or went into the houſe, and leaned his hand on the wal, and a Serpen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bit h m. You doe, ſaith he, very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill to your ſelues, in that you doe ſo raſhly deſire the day of the Lord, for yée ſhall not walke in the light of Gods countenance, becauſe yée haue not beene children of the light, but children of darknes. There noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome darknes ſhall come vpon you, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer you ſhall then aſſay, you ſhall not
<pb facs="tcp:6962:10"/> ſhun terror, you cannot auoid horror: and if you may ſhunne the face of the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> that you render not accompt for your ſins; yet that Beare the Deuill will ronne vpon you, méete you and puniſh you for the ſame. Or if you ſcape this Beare, and enter into the houſe of your conſcience to conſider the euils you haue committed and the good you haue omitted, the tormenting worme will ſeize vpon your conſcience, the worm that <hi>Eſay</hi> 66. ſpeaketh of, <hi>The worme ſhal neuer dy:</hi> And the Euangeliſt <hi>Marke</hi> 9. did teſtifie the ſame; <hi>Their worme dieth not, their fire neuer goeth out, their torments are endleſſe,</hi> neither is there in that day any partiality to be vſed. For the Kings of the earth, Gentlemen, the rich men the great &amp; chiefe Captaines, the mighty men eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bond-man and euery frée-men, ſhall hide themſelues in the dens, and in the rockes of the mountaines, &amp; ſhall ſay to the rocks and mountains fal on vs, and hide vs from the face of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lambe. For ſhe great day of wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand. But when the Son of man ſhall come in the Maieſty of his glory, and the holy Angels with him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom all Nations ſhall be gathered:
<pb facs="tcp:6962:11"/> He ſhall then ſeparate them one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as ſhe ſhepheard diuideth his ſhéepe from the Goats, and he ſhall ſet his ſhéepe on his right hand, and the goats on the left hand; and the King ſhall ſay to them on the right hand, <hi>Mat,</hi> 25. <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my father, inherit the Kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world:</hi> but to them on the left hand hée ſhall ſay; <hi>Depart from me you wicked into euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fire, prepared for the diuell &amp; his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and thoſe ſhall goe into euerlaſting puniſhment; but the righteous into life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall.</hi> To conclude this point heare ſhe Counſell of our Sauiour Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt: <hi>Take heed, leſt at any time your hearts be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with ſurfeting and drunkenneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 2. 34</note> 
               <hi>and cares of this life, and ſo that day come vpon vs vnawares.</hi> For as a ſnare, it ſhall come on all them that dwell on the face of the whole earth: watch yee, and pray al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, that ye may be accounted worthy to eſcape all theſe things that ſhall come to paſſe, and to ſtand before the Sonne of man. Since therefore all theſe things are ſuddenly expected to be fulfilled, and all that reade the Scriptures may heare this, both from Prophets and Apoſtles, nay, and Chriſt himſelfe: <hi>That it is a terrible thing to fall into the hands of the liuing God;</hi> It
<pb facs="tcp:6962:11"/> is a wonder, that ſince all things (as the Apoſtle ſaith) ſhall be diſſolued, that now at length we become not pure, and walke in an holy conuerſation and godlineſſe, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.11</note> and haſting vnto the comming of the day of God. Wherein the Heauens being on fire, <hi>ſhall be diſſolued, and the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall melt with feruent heat.</hi> It is a wonder that we doe not deny all vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, and worldly deſires, and luſts of the fleſh, the glory of the world, the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of riches, and the choaking cares of all earthly things, and exerciſe our ſelues in all ſobriety and godlineſſe, looking for that bleſſed hope,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.3.</note> and the glorious appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance of that great God, and our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. It ought therefore to be our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſt and chiefeſt care, in theſe dangerous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd wicked times, not being drowned in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he imployments of this world, to haue a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are of our owne ſaluation, and to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure the anchor of our hope and ſaith, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur ſoules ſuffer not eternall ſhipwracke. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et vs not perſwade our ſelues that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord is not néer. Let vs not ſay with them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat <hi>Peter</hi> reprehended; where is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe of his comming? For ſince the fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el aſléep, all things continue as they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce the Creation: for how long theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings ſhall continue, the Lord of Hoſts
<pb facs="tcp:6962:12"/> by the Prophet <hi>Haggai</hi> doth declare. <hi>Yet once, it is a little while, and I wil ſhake the heauens and the earth, the Sea, and the dry land.</hi> Now the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> giues the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why he is not yet come.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.9</note> 
               <hi>'Tis his long ſuffering, ſaith he, to vs-wards, not willing that any ſhould periſh but that all ſhould come vnto repentance;</hi> wherefore account that the long ſuffering of the Lord is ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and be diligent, that you may bee found of him in feare, without ſpot and blameleſſe; we muſt be diligent &amp; watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: the <hi>Grecians</hi> are gone aſide, we haue a <hi>Sinon</hi> in vs that will yéeld the place to them: we muſt continually watch, and haue alwayes an eye to the watch, holding our weapons in our hands, vnleſſe wee be minded at all times to be ſurpriſed, and yéeld at the pleaſure of our enemie. For <hi>the day of the Lord commeth as a theefe in the night, in which the Heauens ſhall paſſe away with a great noiſe, and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements ſhall melt with feruent heat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore be yee ready, for in ſuch an houre as you thinke not, the Sonne of man commeth. Now, they that deferre the comming of the Lord, and ſay with that euill ſeruant, My Lord delayeth his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, Let vs eate and drinke, be drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, let them know, <hi>The Lord will come
<pb facs="tcp:6962:12"/> in a day when they looke not for him, and in an houre when they are not aware, and will cut them aſunder, and will giue them their portion with the vnbeleeuers &amp; Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites; where there ſhal be weeping and wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſhing of teeth.</hi> Now,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.3</note> they that know theſe things, and prepare not themſelues, neither doe according to the Will of God, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes: as the ſame Apoſtle Saint <hi>Luke</hi> hath in his Goſpel pronounced. Let vs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour therefore, that when the laſt day cometh, we may ſay with S. <hi>Paule I haue fought a good fight,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.7</note> 
               <hi>I haue finiſhed my courſe; I haue kept the Faith: henceforth there is laid vp for me a crowne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which the Lord that righteous Iudge ſhall giue me that day:</hi> but is this crowne laid vp for thee alone (O <hi>Paul</hi>) not onely for mée (he ſaith) but alſo for them that loue the Lord Ieſus, and expect his appearance.</p>
            <p>Oh that this would take ſome impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the hardeſt of hearts, that doe ſing a temporall <hi>requietem</hi> here vnto their ſoules, leſt while they think the day of the Lord fartheſt from them, it on the ſudden come vpon them, and ſo they be found in a condition too late to be amended, and by no meanes whatſoeuer to be auoided.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6962:13"/>
            <p>To conclude all, gird vp the loynes of your mindes, be ſober, and hope to the end for the glory that is to be brought to you at the reuelation of Ieſus Chriſt, as obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient children, not walking after your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer luſts of ignorance, let your loynes, I ſay, be girded, and your lights burning, and you your ſelues like vnto them that wait for the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uk. 12 15</note> when he wil return from the wedding, that when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth and knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, you may open immediatly: bleſſed is the ſeruant, whom, his Maſter when hée co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth finds ſo doing, of a truth, I ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, he will make him ruler euer all hée hath <hi>Take ye heed, watch and pray, for ye know not when the time is.</hi> For the ſonne of man is as a man taking a far iourney, who left his houſe, and gaue authority to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s ſeruants, and to euery man his worke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mmanding them to waith: <hi>Watch ye therefore, for ye know not when the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter commeth, at euen, at mid-night, or at the cock crowing, leſt comming ſuddenly, he finde you ſleeping,</hi> and ſo caſt you into priſon, there to remaine world without end. From which, the Lord Ieſus kéepe vs all, and that for his mercy ſake alone. To whom he rendred all honour, glory, praiſe and thankeſgiuing, now and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6962:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
